Guide to the Men's Basketball Poster Collection, 1959-2013 UA.01.15.0015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Men's Basketball poster collection
1959-2013
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. University Archives
Duke Blue Devils (Basketball team)
UA.01.15.0015
5 Linear Feet
Basketball team posters are usually produced at the start of a new basketball season, depicting the season's team player lineup and sometimes the game schedule. The Men's Basketball Poster Collection is comprised of posters featuring the Duke Blue Devils Men's Basketball Team.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Men's Basketball Poster Collection was received by the University Archives from several sources: Jim Jarvis in 2015, multiple other sources.
Arrangement
The posters are arranged chronologically.
Collection Overview
The Men's Basketball Poster Collection is comprised of posters featuring the Duke Blue Devils Men's Basketball Team. These posters typically depict the entire team posing for a photograph, sometimes with the team coach; several posters commemorate championship wins or the game results for the season, while a few feature only the Blue Devil or an illustration of some team members. Posters range in size from 12"x18" to 36"x48" with considerable individual variation in size. Posters collected by University Archives from a variety of sources are generally unsigned. Most posters donated by Jim Jarvis were autographed by the entire team and/or Coach Mike Krzyzewski and are mounted on foam core board.
Related Materials
University Archives Poster Collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Men's Basketball Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Athletics Reference Collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Sports Information Office Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Historical note
Basketball was first played at Trinity College in 1906, introduced by then-Athletic Director Wilbur Wade Card. Since then, men's basketball has been played each year at Trinity College and later Duke University, appearing in the NCAA Tournament dozens of times, winning the national championship four times (in 1991, 1992, 2001, and 2010).
Prior to 1980, team posters depicting the Duke Blue Devils men's basketball team in uniform and listing the season's games were often created, as were special publicity and commemorative posters for tournaments, championships, and rivalry games. In 1980, Mike Krzyzewski (Coach K) became head coach of the team, taking over for Bill Foster. Shortly after his arrival, Coach K's wife, Carol "Mickie" Krzyzewski, began a traditional of creating a thematic poster for each season's team. Mrs. Krzyzewski, and later their daughter Debbie Krzyzewski, collaborated with graphic designer Jim Jarvis and others (including photographer Chris Hildreth) to create a new poster every year, using a variety of themes and styles. Basketball team posters are usually produced at the start of a new basketball season, depicting the season's team player lineup and sometimes the game schedule.
Posters; Krzyzewski, Debbie; Krzyzewski, Carol "Mickie"; Jarvis, Jim; Duke University -- Basketball; Duke Blue Devils (Basketball team); Hildreth, Chris; Duke University. University Archives
- Men's Basketball Poster Collection
  - Duke University "Blue Devils", 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes season schedule and advertisement for Pepsi-Cola.
  - Duke Basketball, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Illustration of Blue Devil mascot dunking ball.
  - Off and Running, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "The Spirit Lives On...", 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Duke Basketball Show, 1979 (Map-case OC:IX Top, Folder 1)
    Created by WRAL-TV.
  - 1979-1980 ACC Champions (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A Portrait of Champions, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes season schedule.
  - A Portrait of Champions, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Gene Says Goodbye, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image of Gene "Tinkerbell" Banks and description of his final Blue Devils basketball game against UNC.
  - The Defense Never Rests, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Defense Never Rests, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The "Sixth Man", 1982-1983; 1 Items (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes mounted poster with Adidas logo, and cartoon of man saying "Be One!"
  - World Class, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - World Class, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Right Stuff, 1984-1985; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Right Stuff, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes mounted poster autographed by team.
  - Formula for Success, 1985-1986; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Formula for Success, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ACC Champions, 1985-1986; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - A Banner Year, 1985-1986; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes season results, honors, and awards.
  - Taking Care of Business, 1986-1987; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes one copy autographed by team.
  - Taking Care of Business, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ACC Champions, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Duke 1987, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes season results and player awards.
  - Tradition, 1987-1988; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Tradition, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ACC Champions, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Championship Crowns, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes season results and awards.
  - Encore, 1988-1989; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Encore, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - East Regional Champions, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Heroes, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Red, White, and True Blue, 1989-1990; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Red, White, and True Blue, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes mounted poster autographed by team and Coach K to Jim Jarvis.
  - A Special Team, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Duke's Young Guns, 1990-1991; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Duke's Young Guns, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National Basketball Champions, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Illustration of players and coaches created by Coca-Cola.
  - National Basketball Champions, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Champions! Herald-Sun front page poster, April 2, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Poster version of the front page of the Durham Herald-Sun newspaper with photos and article "Devils bring it home!"
  - Duke's All-American Candidates, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    3H poster featuring Thomas Hill, Bobby Hurley, and Grant Hill.
  - NCAA Champions, 1991; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes season results and awards
  - Where Dreams Begin, 1991-1992; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Where Dreams Begin, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1992 NCAA Champions, 0 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1992 NCAA Champions (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes mounted poster autographed by Coach K to Jim Jarvis.
  - Simply the Best, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Simply the Best, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Defining Duke Basketball, 1993-1994; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Defining Duke Basketball, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - History in the Making, 1994-1995; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - History in the Making, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Networking, 1995-1996; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Networking, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Back in Black, 1996-1997; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Back in Black, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Blue Planet, 1997-1998; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Blue Planet, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Championship Vision, 1998-1999; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Championship Vision, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Forever Duke, 1999-2000; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Forever Duke, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Big Dance, 2000-2001; 3 items (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Vote Coach Krzyzewski Mayor of Bracketville, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Nike promotional poster.
  - Champs! Duke Blue Devils Sports Illustrated cover, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Poster of Sports Illustrated cover featuring Shane Battier.
  - 2001 National Champions, 2 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 2001 National Champions (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Deja Blue, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Deja Blue, 2001-2002 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Duke Rocks, 2002-2003 (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Lights! Cameron! Action!, 2003-2004 (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Vintage, 2004-2005 (Oversize-folder 2)
  - 100 Seasons, 2004 (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Believe, 2006-2007 (Oversize-folder 3)
  - Goodfellas, 2009-2010 (Oversize-folder 3)
  - One, 2010-2011 (Oversize-folder 3)
  - First Class, 2011-2012 (Oversize-folder 4)
  - Fight, 2012-2013 (Oversize-folder 4)